American Montessori Society Records 2006.0230
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Series XXIV: Photographs and Slides, undated, 1907-1980
  - Orpha Mohr, Diabla Valley Montessori School, Lafaette, California, [5x7 print/negative], undated
  - Daniel C. Jordan, [5x7 print], undated
  - Marvin H. Meltzer, [4x5 print], undated
  - Edmund V. Sullivan, Ontario Institute for Studies in Education, Toronto, [b/w snapshot], undated
  - Eileen Mills, Montessori Children's House, San Mateo, California, [5x7 print], undated
  - Louilyn F. Hargett, Montessori Children's House, Morristown, New Jersey, [3x5 color print, c.1 5x7 b/w print, c.2,3 5x7 negative], undated
  - James D. Hennes, [5x7 print], undated
  - Joseph L. Belvedere, [color snapshots], undated
  - Unidentified, [5x7 print - c.1, 2 5x7 negative], undated
  - Christina Marie Trudeau, Montessori Teacher Education, Seattle University, Seattle, Washington, [5x7 print, c.1,2 5x7 negative], undated
  - Douglas Gravel, [8x10 print], 1980
  - Fred M.Hechinger, AMS 20th Anniversary Seminar, [8x10 print], 1980 February 22
  - Douglas Gravel, [8x10 print], undated
  - Tim Seldin, [8x10 print], undated
  - Barbara Anton Grillo, Diablo Valley Montessori School, [3x5 print], 1977
  - Marie M. Dugan, [5x7 print], 1980 June
  - Unidentified, [6x8 print], undated
  - AMS Seminar, New York City, [5x7 prints], 1980
    - Carol Bellamy and Bretta Weiss [c.1-3]
    - Marjorie Farmer, El Comita AMS para Montessorianos De Habla Hispana
    - Mary Shoyinka
    - Jim McGhee, Musya Meyer, Lavonne Plambeck, Joan Indovino
    - Nancy Rambusch, John Blessington, Paul Czaja, Steve Callender [c.1-3]
  - Teacher and children in classroom, [6x10 prints], undated
  - Long Bar Harbor Montessori School, [8x10 print], undated
  - Green Towne School, Philadelphia, [b/w snapshots], undated
  - Moving from 175 Fifth Ave. to 150 Fifth Ave., [snapshots, color and b/w], 1976 September
  - Child from Whitby School putting puzzle together, [6.5x9.5 print], undated
  - Wilmington Montessori Society, [8x10 prints], undated
  - Children's activities at a Montessori School, [varying size prints], undated
  - Children at Suburban Montessori School, Oklahoma, [4x5 prints], undated
  - James D. Hennes, Colorado Department of Education, Denver, [3x4 print, c.1 5x7 print, c.2 5x7 negative], 1973
  - Sister Mary Matz, St.Peter's Montessori School, [5x7 prints, c.1, 2 5x7 negative], undated
  - Judith Brandt, Minneapolis, [3x4 print, c.15x7 print, c.2 5x7 negative], 1976
  - Mary Bernard Pabst, [3x4 color print, c.1.5x7 print, c.1,2 5x7 negative], 1970
  - Nancy Rose and children, Montana Early Learning Center, [3x5 print], 1979
  - Bonnie O'Connor, [5x7 print], undated
  - David Weinberg and Effi Weinberg, 20th Anniversary Seminar Banquet, [5x7 print], undated
  - David Weinberg, [8x10 print], undated
  - Meeting of International Educators at Knesset, Israel, [5x7 print], 1980
  - Montessori Children's House, Adrian, Minnesota, [5x7 print], undated
  - Nancy Rose, Montana Early Learning Center, [5x7 print, c.1,2 ;5x7 negative], 1979
  - Barbara Anton Grillo, Diablo Valley Montessori School, [5x7 print, c.1 5x7 negative], 1977
  - Howard Weiss, [b/w, color snapshots], 1969
  - Robert Pickering, [1x2 color print, c.1-4; 5x7 b/w negative; 3x4 print, c.1-3; 5x7 print, c.4-6; 5x7 negative], undated
  - Schutzman, [4x5 print], 1980
  - Boodman, [3x4 print], 1979
  - Plambeck, [4x5 print], 1979
  - Neubert, [4x5 print], 1980
  - Robert Pickering, Sao Paulo, Brazil, [6.5x9.5 print], 1977
  - Bettye Caldwell, [8x10 print, c.1 5x7 print, c.2 5x7 negative], undated
  - Orpha Mohr, [4x5 print, c.1 5x7 print, c.2], 1974 March 28
  - Paul Michael Li, [2x2 print], undated
  - Patricia Calvert, [2x3 color print; 3x4 color print; 5x7 print, c.2-5; 3x3 print, c.6; 5x7 print, c.1-3; 5x7 negative], 1973-1985
  - Joan H. Lawler, [2x3 color print; color snapshot; 3x3 color print, c.1; 5x7 print, c.2,3; 5x7 negative], 1974, 1977
  - Edward J.Burke, [1x3 print], undated
  - Burton White, [5x7 print], 1980
  - David Elkind, [5x7 print], 1975
  - Jane Mack, Lexington Montessori School, Lexington, MA, [4x5 print], 1974
  - Paul Firestone, New Rochelle Academy Country Day School, [3x4 print], circa 1974
  - Peter Williamson, [4x5 print], undated
  - Urban H. Fleege, [3x5 print, c.1-3], 1980
  - Paul Firestone, New Rochelle Academy Country Day School, circa 1974
  - Virginia Varga, Gloria Dei School, Dayton, Ohio, [5x7 print], 1970
  - Janet Bowes, [5x7 print], 1970
  - Robert A. Morris, Sherwood Montessori School, [3x4 print], undated
  - Suzanne M. Spector, [3x4 print], 1967
  - Suzanne Weiss, [3x5 print], undated
  - Carolyn Bishop, [3x5 color print], 1983
  - Marlene Barron, [5x7 color print], 1983
  - Bonnie Mathisen, [5x7 print], 1983
  - Linnea Friden, [3x4 color print], 1983
  - Paul L. Diamond, [3x4 print], 1983
  - Benjamin D. Boodman, [3x4 print], 1983
  - Robert J. Doman, [4x5 print], 1975
  - Elizabeth M. Carlson, [5x7 print], 1983
  - Randall, [2x3 print], undated
  - Nancy Rambusch, [5x7 prints; 4x5 prints; 8x10 prints; b/w snapshots; 5x7 negative; 4x5 color negatives], undated, 1968-1991
  - Nancy Rambusch and Cleo Monson, [b/w snapshot], 1967
  - Nancy Rambusch, Sister Mary Denise, Mary Bernard Pabst (Rambusch Marathon), [b/w snapshot], circa 1973
  - Jim Ruffing, [b/w snapshot], 1962
  - Children from Glora Dei on Phil Donahue telecast, [8x10 prints], undated
  - Children, Saint Mary's Hall Montessori School, San Antonio, Texas, circa 1980
  - A Montessori school environment, undated
  - Charles V. Bush, [5x7 print], 1983
  - James R. McGhee, Alexander School, Miami, Florida, [5x7 print], undated
  - Maria Montessori, [5x7 print, c.1-3; 5x7 negative], undated
  - Maria Montessori, photo of painting, [5x7 prints, c1-6 5x7 negatives, c.1-2], undated
  - Maria Montessori, London, [5x7 print], 1919
  - Maria Montessori, [5x7 prints, c.1-3], 1912
  - Maria Montessori, International Montessori Congress, San Remo, Italy, [5x7 print, c.1-4], 1949
  - Maria Montessori with children, Los Angeles, [8x10 print, c.1,2; 6x8 print, c.3; 8x10 negative], 1915
  - Maria Montessori with students and children, Vienna, [5x7 print, c.1; 8x10 print, c.2], 1924
  - Maria Montessori, bust [4x5 prints], undated
  - Maria Montessori with children, [8x10 print, c.1-6], 1953 September
  - Maria Montessori, Adjar, India, [8x10 print, c.1; 5x7 print, c.2 5x7 negative], 1939
  - Casa Bambini di Maria Montessori, [8x10 print, c.1; 8x10 negative], 1907
  - Maria Montessori, [8x10 print, c.1,2; 5x7 negative], 1950
  - Maria Montessori, [5x7 print, c.1-3], 1913
  - Children at the Happy Montessori School, Port Washington, New York, [b/w snapshot], undated
  - Convent of the Visitation, [8x10 prints], undated
  - Children at the College of Notre Dame, California, [8x10 prints], undated
  - Green Towne School, Philadelphia, [b/w snapshot], undated
  - Unidentified [b/w snapshots], undated
  - Children, Suburban Montessori School, Oklahoma, [b/w snapshots], undated
  - Sea Pines Academy Montessori School, Hilton Head Island, South Carolina, [8x10 prints], undated
  - Children at Fitchburg Montessori School, Madison, Wisconsin, [4x5 prints], undated
  - Mary Lisa Vertuca and Dr. Marianne McGrath, [4x6 print], undated
  - Susan Shockelford, Meg Zink, and Ginger Fischesser, [4x5 print], undated
  - Child, Wilmington Montessori School, [8x10 print], undated
  - Trabajamas Community Head Start, Bronx, New York, [5x7 print], 1969
  - A Montessori School environment, [4x5 prints], undated
  - Children in Montessori school settings [varying size prints], undated
  - Prepared paths to culture, chart prepared by Ann Udell, Children's House, Philadelphia, [8x10 print; 4x5 negative], 1964
  - Children, Diablo Valley Montessori School, [5x7 prints], 1971
  - AMS Board meeting and seminar, Granby, Colorado, [varying size prints], 1975
    - Nancy Rambush
    - Bob Pickering, et al
    - Professor Howard Bruner of Colorado State University
    - Georgia Grosde, art workshop
    - Jim Hennes
    - J.McVicker Hunt
    - John Bremer
    - [color snapshots]
  - Unidentified, undated
- Series XXV: Unprocessed additions, undated, 1955-2007
  - Bookbag, 2001 (Box 92)
    - Code of Ethics, undated
    - Postcards, undated
    - Fliers, brochures, snapshots, undated
    - Conference materials, 2007
    - Photographs, undated
    - Posters, undated
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Clippings, undated
    - Pins, undated
    - Placque, undated
    - Class notes ( E. Cary; 2 vols.), 1955-1956
  - T-shirt (Annual Conference), 2006 (Box 93)
    - T-shirts, caps (Annual Conference), 2007
  - Publications, fliers, posters, mailings, 2 VHS tapes, 4 audio cassette tapes (Annual Conference), 2007 (Box 94)
  - Brochures, banner, ephemera, grant proposal, clippings, programs, CDs, 1958-2008 (Box 95)
- Series XXVI: 2011 Additions, undated
  - Subseries A: Organizational records, undated, 1951-2011
    - Notebooks, undated, 1962-1964 (Box 2011-0058_1)
      Includes: Montessori Mathematics by Gretchen Courage, The Montessori Elementary School and its Curriculum from Montessori Development Foundation, AMS Seminar Brochures, and Training Manual.
    - They come to Learn and Serve--Montessori for Parents and Teachers. A report on 10 months of workshops, by J.E. Rash, undated
    - Books, undated
      Creative and Holistic, Developmentally Responsibe Learning Environment that Empowers the early adolescent, Elisabeth Johnson Coe; Building the Foundations for Creative learning, Urban H. Fleege, editor; Montessori Curriculum in Minnesota and Wisconsin Public Montessori Elementary Schools, Michael James Dorer.
    - Articles and Publications, undated, 1967-1995 (Box 2011-0058_2)
      Includes: "A pediatrician looks at Montessori for neurologically impaired children," by Sylvia O. Richardson; "Peace and Education" Maria Montessori; "A balanced diet of toys," Illinois Montessori Society; "Basic characteristics of a Montessori program for children ages 3-6," American Montessori Society; "Exercise therapy for body coordination," Edward G. Scagliotta; "Montessori Philosophy and Educational Theory," David R. Weinberg; "Montessori, Teachers and the role of researcher," John Chattin McNichols ( Montessori Life, Winter 1992); "Non-violences and the Child" and "The dignity of the Child," A. M. Joosten; "Presentation of a second language in a Montessori Class," Marcia H. Bernet ( Constructive Triangle, Fall 1967); "Questions Parents ask about Montessori kindergarten," American Montessori Society; "The Montessori Method and the Kindergarden: Text and Context of the U.S. Bureau of Education Bulletin," edited by R. Calvert Orem; "The Montessori Method," Beatrice Hessen; "Montessori Manual for parents of preschoolers;" "Manual for developing, evaluating and accrediting professional preparation program plans for Montessori teacher certification;" "Reconstructing in Education," Maria Montessori; "The Montessori Approach to discipline," Lena L. Gitter; Montessori Life (v.23 #2); Montessori Index, Virginia B. Vleege; Montessori Schools in America: Historical, Philosophical and emperical research perspectives, John Chattin McNichols, editor.
    - Notes, undated
      Includes: "Why continue on into the elementary level of Montessori?"
    - Publications, undated, 1980-2000
      Includes: Comparison of Montessori and Skill-Based language arts instruction with kindergarden children in a Title I school, Swee-Chin J. Kuan-Lua; Learner centered education, Thodor F. Naumann and Bobbie Parson; Maria Montessori and modern educational thought, Lawrence Jerome Foster; Toward an understanding of the effects of the Montessori educational system, James Joseph Choquette; AMS Teacher Member Directory (1999-2000); AMS 20th Anniversary Seminar (1980); Proceedings of the American Montessori Society (1976); Public School Montessorian (v. 7, #2 and v.8 n.1).
    - Reports, 1998-2010 (Box 2011-0058_3)
      Includes: Annual report, AMS School Accreditation task force report, The Montessori School management guide, Whitby School.
    - Publications, undated, 1961, 2004-2005
      Includes: Barrington Courier-Review (7/29/2004); "Recruiting Montessori Teachers;" The Saturday Evening Post (9/23/1961); invitation (2005); "Christians in Action," Nancy Rambush; Keeping up with Whitby/Alumni News (Fall/Winter 1997); "Joy of Learning" (1961); Learning how to learn, Nancy McCormick Rambush and George N. Shuster; Montessori Life (v.7 #1); Whitby School handbook; brochures and articles (Whitby School).
    - Conference materials, 2003-2011
      Includes: Fliers, advertizements, program, bookmark, postcards.
    - Photographs, moving images, optical disks, undated, 2004-2010
      Includes: Archive committee meeting; unidentified event; Maria Montessori; AMS staff; JoAnn Deak (10/14/2010); Interview with John McDermott, Ketih Whitescarver, Jackie Conssentino and Phyllis Povell; Joyce Pickering (10/23/2010)
    - Nancy McCormick Rambush, undated, 1951-1995
      Includes: Correspondence ( Bob Rambush to Kobenhavn Montessori Center), marriage certificate, fliers, eulogy, obituaries, rememberance, sympathy cards.
    - Photographs, undated, 2006
      Includes: AMS Living Legacies Aline Wolf, Peggy Loeffler and Celma Perry; Children (possibly Leslie Birmingham); St. Michael's College ( Toronto, Canada).
- Series XXVII: 2012 Additions
  - Three DVDs of interviews done at the AMS 2012 Annual Conference: (Box 2012-0058_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Judi Bauerlein, Sr. Christina Trudeau, Judy Townsend.]
- Series XXVIII: 2013 Additions, 1978-2007
  - National Center for Montessori Education, 1978-2007
    - 1979-2007 (Box 2013-0014_1)
      Awards, examinations, conference programs, administrative records, correspondence, notes, clippings, photocopies, financial records, publications, realia (hat and flags)
    - 1978-2004 (Box 2013-0014_2)
      Administrative records, notes, correspondence, fliers, photocopies of awards, financial records, legal documents, map, photographs